Now we'll look at insertion sort,
现在我们将学习插入排序
which is another elementary method that interestingly has quite
这是另外一种基本排序方法 有趣的是
different performance characteristics than selection sort.
相比选择排序 插入排序具有相当不同的性能
Let's look at a demo of insertion sort.
让我们来看看一个插入排序的演示
For insertion sort, what we're going to do is we'll move an index i
对于插入排序，我们要做的和之前一样 从左到右移动索引 i
from left to right as before, but now, in the i'th iteration,
但现在，在第 i个迭代中
we're going to move a[i] into position among the elements to its left.
我们将会把 a[ i ] 移动到其左侧的位置
Let's look at how that works on our example with cards.
让我们用牌的示例来看看这是怎么工作的
So, now we start by initializing i at the first card, and
现在我们从初始化 i为第一张牌开始
we take the idea that everything from i to its left is going to be sorted, and
我们的想法是 i的左边的一切将会被排序
everything from the right we're not going to look at at all.
右边的一切，我们全部都不去看
So everything to the left of i is in ascending order, everything to the right,
所以，i 左侧所有的东西是升序，右侧所有的东西
we haven't seen it all yet.
我们现在还没检查过
So now when we increment i, well, in this case it's already in order,
现在我们增加 i 好，在这种情况下它已经排好序了
we don't have anything else to do.
我们什么也不用做
In the third case now, when i is at the third entry in the array,
在第三种情况下，当 i 是数组中的第三项时
now we start a index j, and we move that starting at i to the left.
此时我们从索引 j 开始 然后，j 从 i 开始向左边移动
And what we need to do is just exchange the 5 with every element to its left
我们要做的是将5与它左边
that's greater.
更大的元素交换
So first we exchange it with the 10, it's still not in place, so
那么，首先与10交换，依然没有到最终位置
we exchange it with the 7.
所以再和7交换
Now we get to the beginning of the array, and once we've done that or
现在已经到数组最前面了，一旦我们检查完左侧所有项或者
we've hit a smaller element, then we have everybody to the left of i in order.
找到一个更小的元素，i 左边所有项就排好序了
So now we increment that again, and we come to the 3.
再将 i 加一，这次的牌是3
Again, we exchange as long as the card immediately to the left is greater.
一样的，只要左侧相邻的牌更大，就一直交换
And once we've done that,
一旦完成之后
then we have everything to the left by in ascending order.
从 i 开始它左侧的数组就是升序的
Now, in this case, we have the 8, and we only have to exchange one, and
这个情况中，牌是8，只需要交换一次
now it's got the 7 to its left and everything is in order.
现在左边是7，i 左边就都排好序了
So we've achieved putting it in order with less work in this case.
所以这个情形中我们用更少的工作量就完成了排序
We don't always have to go all the way back to the beginning.
并不总是需要一直检查到数组的开头
4, exchange it with everybody to its left that's greater,
4，将它和左边所有比它大的牌交换
until we find a smaller element, then it's in ascending order.
直到找到更小的元素，然后 i 的左边就是升序了
2 has to go all the way back to the beginning.
2，需要一直检查到数组的开头
But then the very next one, the 9 has to only go back one position,
而紧接着的下一个，9只需要移动一个位置
and the 6 has to go about halfway back.
6差不多需要移动到中间
And then we have the entire array sorted.
然后整个数组就排好序了
Again, we can look at insertion sort in terms of invariants.
我们在从不变式的角度来看插入排序
Our pointer still scans from left to right, but
指针依然是从左至右扫描
now the elements to the left of the pointer, including it,
但是指针左边的所有元素，包括指针指向的元素
are in order, but the elements to the right have not yet been seen at all.
都是排好序的，而右边的元素都还完全没有检查过
So we have to look at the code that's going to maintain that invariant as
我们来看随着指针递增维持
the pointer increments.
不变式的代码
Move the pointer to the right, it's incremented again.
将指针向右侧移动，增加1
Now the invariant's broken because the element on
因为指针指向的元素没排过序
the pointer is not in sorted order.
所以破坏了不变式
To put it in sorted order, we have to move from right to left, exchanging it with
要将它排序，需要将它和左边每个
every larger elements to its left, and that's what the code at the bottom does.
更大的元素交换，下面的代码完成的就是这个
It starts j at i, and decrements j,
索引 j 从 i 开始，逐渐变小
exchanging j with the elements to its left,
j 指向的元素与左边的元素交换
a of j with the element to its left, a of j-1,
a[j] 与左边的元素 a[j-1] 交换
as long as a of j is less than a of j-1 or j is bigger than 0.
只要a[j]小于a[j-1]并且 j > 0就一直交换
And that immediately gives this code for insertion sort,
我们就马上得到了插入排序的代码
which is similar to our code for selection sort and just as simple.
与选择排序的代码类似，而且一样简单
It's got two nested for loops, selection sort had two nested for loops,
有两个嵌套的for循环，选择排序也是一样的
a test, a comparison, and an exchange inside the for loop.
循环中需要进行一次检查，一次比较大小，和一次交换
And that's a fine implementation of an elementary sorting method.
这是基本排序方法的一个良好的实现
What about the analysis of insertion sort?
插入排序的分析是怎样的呢？
It's more complicated.
插入排序更复杂一些
Our proposition says that insertion sort, to sort randomly ordered array
我们的命题是对具有不同关键值的随机序列排序
with distinct keys, it'll use about one quarter N squared compares,
插入排序平均需要使用大约1/4 N^2次比较
and about the same number, one quarter N squared exchanges, on the average.
与大约相同的交换次数 1/4 N^2
This is more complicated to prove.
这个要证明的话更复杂一些
It depends on the array being randomly ordered.
和随机顺序的数组有关
And again, you can get a feeling for
和选择排序的证明一样，从这个N×N的算法步骤中
where the proposition comes from by looking at this N by N trace.
你可以找到命题来源的思路
Again, the black elements are the ones that we compare, and
黑色的元素依然是我们比较的
actually, they're also the exchanges.
实际上，也是进行的交换
On the red one is the one that's finally put into place.
红色的是到达的最终位置
And you can see that for a large array that's randomly ordered, the element
你可以看到对于随机顺序的大数组
that we put into place is going to go about halfway back on the average.
要移动到最终位置平均要移动大约一半的位置
So that means about half the elements below the diagonal are going to be black
这意味着对角线以下的元素
on the average.
平均一半是黑色的
There's N squared over 2 below the diagonal,
对角线以下的元素有1/2 N^2个
half of that is N squared over 4.
一半就是1/4 N^2
The exact analysis is not much more detailed than that.
精确的分析比这个详细不了多少
This is a bigger trace that shows, again,
这个步骤更多，再次显示
about half the elements below the diagonal are involved in the sort.
排序过程中涉及到对角线下大约一半的元素
[COUGH] Let's look at an animation.
我们来看动画
Since N squared over 4 versus N squared over 2,
因为1/4 N^2和1/2 N^2相比小一半
insertion sort's going to be about twice as fast as selection sort.
插入排序的速度大约是选择排序的两倍
So we can do about twice as many items in the trace in the same amount of time.
所以相同时间内演示中我们能够对大约两倍的元素进行排序
It grabs an element and brings it back into position every time.
每次选取一个元素，将它移动到左边合适的位置
So that's an animation for randomly ordered items.
这是随机顺序元素的动画
Now, insertion sort does depend on the initial order of the data.
插入排序运行时间取决于数据开始的顺序
Let's look at the best case and the worst case, which are certainly outliers.
我们来看看最好与最坏的情况，当然这些都是异常情况了
If the array happens to be already sorted, all insertion sort
如果数组恰好已经排好序了，插入排序
does is really validate that each element has got smaller elements to its left.
实际上只需要验证每个元素比它左边的元素大
So it does no exchanges.
所以不用进行交换
It gets the sorting job done with just N minus 1 compares.
只需要N - 1次比较就能完成排序工作
On the other hand, if the array is in descending order and
另一方面，如果数组是降序排列的并且
has no duplicates, then every element goes all the way back.
不存在重复值，每个元素都移动到数组开头
It makes n squared over 2 compares and n squared over 2 exchanges.
需要进行1/2 N^2 次比较与1/2 N^2 次交换
So in the first case, it's much,
所以第一种情况下，插入排序比选择排序快得多
much faster than selection sort, linear instead of quadratic.
是线性时间的而不是平方时间的
In the second case, it's slower than selection sort,
第二种情形中，比选择排序慢
because it uses about the same number of compares, but it uses many more exchanges.
因为需要一样的比较次数，但是多得多的交换次数
So let's see that in the animation.
我们来看动画
So this is when the items come in in reverse order.
这是元素降序排列的情况
Now, every time it gets a new item,
每次得到一个新元素
it has to exchange it all the way back to the beginning.
都必须一直交换到最开头
Same kind of dynamic characteristic as selection sort, except, for
与选择排序的动态特性相同
every step, it's not just comparing,
不同点在于，每一步中插入排序不仅仅是交换
it's also exchanging, which makes it even slower in practice.
还要进行交换，所以实际中就慢了很多
So this is a bad case that we wouldn't like to see in a practical application.
这是实际应用中我们不想见到的最坏的情况
But there's also a good case that actually we take advantage of in plenty of
但也有好的情况，在很多实际应用中我们
practical applications.
都在利用这一点
And that has to do with when the array is partially sorted.
就是数组已经部分有序的情况
To talk about this in a quantitative way, we define what's called an inversion.
用定量的方法考虑，我们定义“逆序对”(inversion)
An inversion is just a pair of keys that are out of order in the array.
逆序对是数组中乱序的关键值对
So this array has six inversions, T and
比如这个数组中有六个逆序对
R are out of order, because R should go before T.
T和R是乱序的，因为R应该在T的前面
T and P are out of order, and so forth.
T和P是乱序的，等等
This array has six inversions.
这个数组中有六个逆序对
And we define an array to be partially sorted if its number of
我们这样定义一个数组是部分有序的，如果其逆序对
inversions is linear, if it's less than some constant times N.
数量是线性的，或者说比N乘以某个常数小
And partially sorted arrays appear often in practice.
部分有序的数组在实际应用中经常遇到
For example, if you have a large array with just a few, that's sorted except for
例如，有一个大数组是有序的，只有最后加上的
just a few unsorted elements appended at the end,
几个元素是无序的
it's going to be partially sorted.
这个数组就是部分有序的
Or in other cases, if you only have a few entries out of place,
或者另外的情况，只有几个项不在最终位置
the array's going to be partially sorted.
数组就是部分有序的
These types of things arise often in practical applications.
实际应用中经常出现这样的东西
And what's interesting about insertion sort is that it runs in linear time for
插入排序有意思的地方在于对于部分有序的数组
partially sorted arrays.
它的运行时间是线性的
And the proof is, the number of comparisons and the number of exchanges is
证明就是交换的次数
equal to the number of exchanges equal to the number of inversions, and
与逆序对的个数相等
there's an extra compare for every element except the first.
而除过第一个元素外每个元素需要多一次比较
So let's look at how that looks in the animation.
我们来看动画
Here's a partially sorted array, and
这是一个部分有序的数组
you can see that insertion sort quickly gets the job done.
可以看到插入排序很快完成了工作
We're going to take advantage of this a little bit later in this lecture.
这门课稍后我们将利用这个性质
That's insertion sort, our second elementary sorting method.
这就是插入排序 我们学习的第二个基本排序方法